You can find home remedies
for all sorts of ailments,
but the science doesn’t
always back them up.
What does it have to say
about using a common
household product on warts?
"Removing Warts with Duct Tape"
When I was reviewing the science behind
common over-the-counter remedies
used in dermatology such as tea
tree oil for acne or nail fungus,
I was surprised to see on the same
page a section on duct tape.
Duct tape?!
The only time I remember seeing
duct tape used in a medical study
was on the identification of the gases
responsible for the odor of human farts,
which involved a collection system
comprised of gas-tight pantaloons
sealed to the skin with duct tape.
That's the study where they
assessed the wind breaking ability
of a cushion called
the Toot Trapper.
But what the dermatology journal
was talking about is warts.
Duct tape brings out our
inventive, slightly kooky side.
Given this versatility, it wasn't
so surprising a few years ago
when a group of doctors reported
that duct tape could get rid of warts.
As I noted in my last wart video,
all sorts of strange things
are purported to cure warts
because most go away on their own.
A thousand kids were
followed for two years
and two-thirds of the warts
disappeared without doing a thing.
So maybe we should
just leave them alone,
although there are cases
that may warrant treatment.
Otherwise we can just let our
own body take care of them.
Warts are caused by wart viruses, and
so spontaneous wart disappearance
is assumed to be an immune response
where our body finally wakes up
and takes notice.
This assumption
is based on studies like this—where
foreign proteins were injected into
the wart itself, like a measles-mumps-
rubella vaccine straight into the wart—
which compared to placebo, appeared to
accelerate the immune clearance process.
The problem, of course, is that
injections hurt, and 30% of the kids
that got their warts injected with the
vaccine suffered a flu-like syndrome.
Yikes! OK, scratch that.
What else do we got?
Within a few months any placebo treatment
will work in about a quarter of the cases.
So if you put duct tape on 100 warts and
23 go away, that wouldn't mean much.
The traditional medical therapies, acid
treatments and freezing treatments,
bump the cure rate up to about 50%.
So if you were really serious about
testing the efficacy of duct tape,
you would pit it head to head
against one of those,
and that's exactly what happened.
The efficacy of duct tape vs cryotherapy
in the treatment of the common wart.
Cryotherapy is one of the treatments
of choice for many pediatricians.
Objective: To determine if application
of duct tape is as effective
as cryotherapy in the treatment
of common warts.
Patients were randomized to receive
either liquid nitrogen applied
to each wart or
duct tape occlusion.
When I heard about treating
warts with duct tape,
I had this image where they were like
trying to rip them off or something.
No, no, no, no. They're just applying a
little circle of duct tape every week or so.
Here are the details...
Although there had been a few
anecdotal reports of using tape,
no prospective, randomized controlled
trial had yet been performed until
this study, which found that the duct
tape was not only equal to but exceeded
the efficacy of cryotherapy, which
worked in 60% of the cases,
but 85% of the duct tape
patients were cured—significantly
more effective than cryotherapy
for treatment of the common wart.
More effective and fewer side effects.
The only adverse effect observed
in the duct tape group during
our study was a small,
minimal amount of local irritation and
redness, whereas cryotherapy hurts.
You want to hear the saddest thing?
One young child actually vomited in fear
of pain before each cryotherapy session.
They were like torturing the poor kid.
Cryotherapy can cause pain and
bloody blisters that can get infected
and mess up your nail bed.
So, duct tape: more effective, fewer
side effects and more convenient.
Compare applying a little duct tape at
home to making multiple clinic visits,
dragging the poor kid
back every two weeks.
I mean it's like a win-win-win.
Duct tape can now be offered
as a nonthreatening, painless,
and inexpensive technique for
the treatment of warts in children.
I mean how much does a
little piece of duct tape cost?
It's like a win-win-win-win.
Ah, but the money you save
is the money the doctor loses.
There's no way the medical profession is
going to just let this go unchallenged.
Further studies were performed
and failed to show an effect,
and so we end up in the medical
literature with conclusions like this:
"Is duct tape effective
for treating warts?"
Bottom line?
No. Huh.
Is duct tape really not
effective after all,
or was there some kind of critical
design flaw in the follow-up studies?
We'll find out next.
One of the unusual, innovative,
and long-forgotten remedies noted
in this dermatology journal was
the use of duct tape to cure warts,
finally put to the test.
There's all sorts of
conventional therapies
from acid to cryosurgery to
lasers, but most of these
are expensive, or painful, or both.
Whereas the simple application
of duct tape is neither—
and may even be more effective
than trying to freeze the warts off.
Some doctors lauded the study,
noting they had been using
duct tape for decades as a
painless yet effective treatment,
as opposed to surgery and
other destructive therapies.
The only downside being your patients
may think you're off your rocker,
but hey, when it works, they appreciate
your wise choice to minimize discomfort.
Other doctors were not so amused.
Here they are spending money
on all this fancy equipment
and then along comes duct tape?
Studies like that "could damage
the reputation of cryosurgery,"
complaining that the 10-second
application of liquid nitrogen
they used in the study was too short,
so it was an unfair comparison.
And evidently you really have
to get in there and freeze
until they get a blistering reaction.
And yes, it hurts but too bad,
even making light of the poor child
who vomited out of fear of the pain
prior to each freezing by
making some joke about it.
Did they have a point, though, about
the 10 seconds? Well, in the duct tape
versus cryotherapy trial those
10-second cryotherapy treatments
worked 60% of the time, which
is actually better than the results
of most cryotherapy studies that
only seemed to cure about 50%.
In fact, the typical cryotherapy
for warts works so poorly that
statistically it didn't even beat out
placebo, so all that pain may be
for nothing, though aggressive
cryotherapy does seem to work better.
See, what they should have done,
wrote another doctor in response
to the duct tape trial, is take a scalpel
to it and then really blister it up,
and then you go back a week later and
try to cut and crater it out, and then
maybe go back a third time, bragging that
they can get closer to a 90% cure rate.
Yeah, but at what cost?
In the duct tape trial one
patient lost his study wart
in a trampoline toe-amputation accident.
Hey, there's a treatment that works,
100% effective: amputation!
But at what cost?
Eighty-five percent of the duct tape
patients were cured with no pain
or tissue damage, whereas aggressive
cryotherapy may require lidocaine
injection, nerve blocks, to take
the "cry out of cryotherapy"
and can cause permanent tissue damage.
You can end up with these
big necrotic frostbite lesions.
I mean in one sense tissue damage is
the whole point of freezing warts,
but you can end up causing these deep
burns or end up rupturing tendons,
which can cause permanent disability or
cause extensive scarring in rare cases.
Just the psychological stress
of having to keep going back
for this painful procedure may
ironically impair our ability
to fight off the wart viruses
in the first place.
And so even if the effectiveness of duct
tape is shown to be merely equivalent
to that of cryotherapy, it would
be better; and it was shown to be
even more effective,
in fact maybe most effective.
Compared to 10 other wart treatments,
duct tape beat out them all
in terms of effectiveness,
and also in terms of cost—
cheaper than all but the DN option,
which stands for Do Nothing.
Compared to the most cost-effective
prescription treatments available,
OTC duct tape, meaning over-the-counter
duct tape, is 10 times cheaper.
It's an unusual and welcome event in
health care when a common ailment
is proven equally amenable
to an inexpensive, tolerable,
and safe alternative therapy.
But wait.
If you look at the latest
Cochrane review, which is like
the gold-standard of evidence-based
reviews, they acknowledge that
cryotherapy is less convenient,
more painful, more expensive.
But while in the earlier review they
did get excited about the effectiveness
of duct tape, in two subsequent studies
duct tape seemed to totally flop.
So should we give up
on duct tape for warts
or is there another side of the story?
We'll find out in the
thrilling conclusion next.